One very important concept to understand with
these roles is that SQL has distinct levels
of roles for server tasks and database tasks.
The roles you just saw, all being server-level
roles, do not give users access to individual
databases.
For users to have permissions on databases,
those permissions either need to be granted
specifically or through one or more database
roles.
I will expand the AdventureWorks2019 database
and then Security, Roles, and Database Roles.
As we cover these roles, again, focus on the
purpose of roles, which is to control permissions
on, in this case, a database.
Going from least restrictive to most restrictive,
let's start with the db_owner role, which
has complete control on a database, including
the ability to drop the database.
Next, we have the db_securityadmin role, which
allows one to manage membership of custom
roles and manage overall permissions on a
database.
Thirdly, we have the db_accessadmin role,
which can add or remove access for Windows
accounts and groups and SQL accounts to and
from a database.
Earlier I mentioned that the ability to restore
databases is a server role.
For backups, however, the db_backupoperator
role is assigned to each database.
The reasoning behind doing these roles on
these levels is: restores need to happen quickly,
so a person in that role should be able to
restore any database on a server.
Backups happen on different schedules depending
upon the volume of data being backed up and
the needs for data to be as current as possible
should it need to be restored.
The db_ddladmin role can run any data definition
language command, which includes CREATE, ALTER,
and DROP commands, the latter being the main
reason administrators need to be careful as
to who receives this role.
The db_datawriter role allows one to add,
change, or delete data to, in, or from any
table in a database.
The db_datareader role allows for viewing
any data in tables or filtered data through
views.
There are two explicit deny roles that can
be placed on users in a database.
The db_denydatawriter role prevents those
in that role from adding data to, deleting
data from, or modifying data in a database.
The db_denydatareader role prevents one from
reading data in tables and views.
Lastly, the public role for a database is
the same as that of the public role for the
server except, of course, the role is at the
database level and whatever permissions are
granted to the role apply to anyone with an
account assigned to the database.
Before leaving this topic, the deny permissions
bring up an interesting point: why use them
when we can just keep people in the public
role?
The reason: these two roles ensure that certain
users can be prevented from ever reading data
or changing data even if a group they belong
to has access to a database.